Guide to the Graham A. Hill collection AD.MC.052
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Graham Anthony Hill papers
1956-2000
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Hill, Graham Anthony
AD.MC.052
0.4 Linear Feet in 1 document box, and one poster in oversize map file.
Photographs, broadsheets, documents, periodicals and book, related chiefly to the military service of Graham Anthony Hill, an officer with the British Army, who served with the Trucial Oman Scouts and Union Defence Force, in the early 1970s, in the Trucial States and later, the United Arab Emirates.
Conditions governing access
The Graham A. Hill papers are open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room at New York University Abu Dhabi.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired by purchase, 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three parts: Biographical, photographs, and printed material and ephemera. Items are further arranged within these groups by folder title, in rough alphabetic order.
Biographical note
Graham Anthony Hill was born around 1934, and raised in Devon, England, in a town near Exeter. In some records, his name is alternately presented as Antony Graham Hill. Little biographical information is available about him, but military records show that he was a British Army cadet who was placed on the National Service List as a second lieutenant with the Regular Army, in Devon and Dorset, in April 1959, and was promoted to the rank of Lieutenant in the Wessex Brigade of the Territorial Army in December 1960, and transferred at that rank to the Gloucestershire Regiment in December 1962. [Source: Supplement to the London Gazette, https://www.thegazette.co.uk/, accessed November 2019]. He appears to have remained with the Gloucestershire Regiment for the remainder of his military career, and judging from the contents of his archive, may have served in Cyprus and in Aden during the 1960s, among other locations.
In 1970, he was seconded to the Trucial Oman Scouts, where he served in the Trucial States in the emirate of Sharjah, training local recruits at a base near the town of Manama. Following the union of the United Arab Emirates in December 1971, he remained in this post, now serving with the Union Defence Force. After his departure from the United Arab Emirates in 1974, he served elsewhere until his retirement from the British Army at the rank of Major in June 1977. Documents in his papers show that he was employed as a civilian contractor in Jubail, Saudi Arabia, in 1979. He subsequently returned to England, and some veterans of the Trucial Oman Scouts remember having seen him living in Exeter in his later years.
Scope and contents
The Graham A. Hill papers consist of photographs, broadsheets, documents, periodicals and a book, related chiefly to the military service of Graham Anthony Hill with the Trucial Oman Scouts and Union Defence Force, in the early 1970s, in the Trucial States and later, the United Arab Emirates.
Photographs, some produced by the Royal Air Force, others taken presumably by Hill or other military personnel he knew, document training exercises and parades at the training camp in Manama (Ajman), circa 1971-1972; images of leaders of the emirate of Dubai, including Sheikh Rashid bin Saeed al Maktoum and his son, Sheikh Mohammed bin Rashid, inspecting a newly constructed military facility in 1973; images of Sharjah and surrounding areas of the northern Emirates, circa early 1970s; and personal snapshots from Hill of friends and colleagues. Also included are postcards sent by Hill to his family in England during a trip to Israel in 1960; photographs, presumably of locations in the Eastern Mediterranean, circa 1960s.
The collection also includes three publications related to Hill's period in the Emirates, newsletters from the Trucial Scouts Officers Association (1999-2000); six broadsheets in Arabic offering rewards for turning in various types of weapons, a wanted poster related to suspected insurgents in Aden, and a poster in Arabic and English warning against entry into a military installation (the last two items have not been definitively identified, but are likely from Aden in the mid-1960s).
The collection is divided into three parts: Biographical, photographs, and printed material and ephemera. The Biographical section contains a few items that could help with identifying who Graham A. Hill was, and includes identification cards, correspondence to his parents, and material from the Trucial Oman Scouts Association. The Photographs form the bulk of the collection, including both official and informal photographs, some taken by Hill, some taken by the Royal Air Force, and others by unidentified photographers, including friends of Hill. Handwritten notations identifying locations or individuals are written on the verso of several images. The Printed Material and Ephemera portion of the collection included material collected by Hill about or related to the region, and usually contemporary to his time there.
Great Britain. Trucial Oman Scouts; Shāriqah, United Arab Emirates; ʻAjmān, United Arab Emirates; Dubayy, United Arab Emirates; Aden (Yemen); Maktūm, Rāshid ibn Saʻīd, 1906-; Al Maktoum, Mohammed bin Rashid, 1949-; Trucial Oman Scouts Association
- Biographical, 1960-2000
  - Correspondence, sent to parents and sister, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Identification documents, Saudi Arabia, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trucial Oman Scouts Association, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1970-1975, and undated
  - Ajman (Manama) or Sharjah: Passing Out Parade, (photos credited to R.A.F.), 28 black and white prints, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dubai, ruling family: inspection of military facility, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General
    Depicts members of ruling family (al Maktoum), inspecting military base with British personnel. Includes ruler Sheikh Rashid bin Saeed, his sons, Sheikh Mohammed bin Rashid and Sheikh Hamdan bin Rashid, along with various British officers identified on verso of images. 8 black and white images, 1973.
  - Hill, and other British military personnel at leisure, undated, (19 color prints, 4 sleeves of negatives), undated, circa 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Plastic album: contains black and white images of or related to Sharjah (39 images), and other parts of the Northern Emirates, 144 images, undated, circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Images include some of city and port of Sharjah, others of military personnel at base where Hill served as commander, with images of Hill and Emirati personnel, totalling 39 images. Also contains color snapshots, likely from associated or friend of Hill, depicting travels through region, including Oman, 105 prints.
  - Unidentified, album pages, undated, circa 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Album pages, with photos affixed (14 pages, recto and verso, with 26 black and white prints, 1 color): scenes from desert landscape, military camps and personnel, unidentified locations, likely northern United Arab Emirates.
  - Unidentified: primary landscapes in Eastern Mediterranean, with a couple of images of Hill (23 black and white images), Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Various, 1975 and undated, circa 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Depicts Hill with friends at U.S. – Mexico border, 1975 (1 image, color); female companion of Hill at beach and pool, UAE, circa early 1970s (12 images, color); unidentified desert location and people (5 images, black and white), former comrade of Hill and wife, at beach (1 image, color), image of several young men, including Hill, with caption on back "The Magnificent Seven," in paper sleeve, undated, circa 1960s.
- Printed material and ephemera, 1956-1976
  - Aden: map of, undated, circa mid-1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Aden: leaflets concerning found weapons, undated, circa mid-1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Aden: poster, "Protected Place, No Entry Without Permission," English and Arabic text, with silhouette figure of sentry, July 1965 (Map-case 3.1)
  - Aden: wanted poster depicting suspected insurgents, undated, circa mid-1960s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Akhbar Dubai = Dubai News (Arabic periodical), July 12, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Globe and Laurel: the journal of the Royal Marines [U.K.], May-June 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Article about the end of the Trucial Oman Scouts / Union Defence Force on pages 168-169
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1973, and undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Two notes related to photographs located elsewhere in collection, 1971-1972; newspaper clippings about replacement of British officers with Emirati personnel in Abu Dhabi Defence Force and Union Defence Force, 1973; one banknote, for ten Lebanese pounds, issued by Bank of Syria and Lebanon, 1956; and typescript copy of satiric doggerel poetry written by unidentified staff of al-Saada, the firm Hill worked for in Saudi Arabia in 1979, titled "The Rubayyat of Terry Al-Saada Khayyam."
  - Sharjah 1970 (London: Middle East Economic Digest) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Trucial Oman Scouts Word List, issued by Trucial Oman Scouts (Dubai: National Printing Press), December 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)